<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <id>1244</id>
  <CoreStandardVersion>1.1</CoreStandardVersion>
  <title>How to Read the Standards</title>
  <content>&lt;h2&gt;Overall Document Organization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standards comprise three main sections: a comprehensive K-5 section and two content area-specific sections for grades 6-12, one for ELA and one for history/social studies, science, and technical subjects. Three appendices accompany the main document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each section is divided into strands. K-5 and 6-12 ELA have Reading, Writing, Speaking and Listening, and Language strands; the 6-12 history/social studies, science, and technical subjects section focuses on Reading and Writing. Each strand is headed by a strand-specific set of College and Career Readiness Anchor Standards that is identical across all grades and content areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standards for each grade within K-8 and for grades 9-10 and 11-12 follow the CCR anchor standards in each strand. Each grade-specific standard (as these standards are collectively referred to) corresponds to the same-numbered CCR anchor standard. Put another way, each CCR anchor standard has an accompanying grade-specific standard translating the broader CCR statement into grade-appropriate end-of-year expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual CCR anchor standards can be identified by their strand, CCR status, and number (R.CCR.6, for example). Individual grade-specific standards can be identified by their strand, grade, and number (or number and letter, where applicable), so that RI.4.3, for example, stands for Reading, Informational Text, grade 4, standard 3 and W.5.1a stands for Writing, grade 5, standard 1a. Strand designations can be found in brackets alongside the full strand title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who is responsible for which portion of the Standards?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single K-5 section lists standards for reading, writing, speaking, listening, and language across the curriculum, reflecting the fact that most or all of the instruction students in these grades receive comes from one teacher. Grades 6-12 are covered in two content area-specific sections, the first for the English language arts teacher and the second for teachers of history/social studies, science, and technical subjects. Each section uses the same CCR anchor standards but also includes grade-specific standards tuned to the literacy requirements of the particular discipline(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key Features of the Standards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading: Text complexity and the growth of comprehension&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Reading standards place equal emphasis on the sophistication of what students read and the skill with which they read. Standard 10 defines a grade-by-grade "staircase" of increasing text complexity that rises from beginning reading to the college and career readiness level. Whatever they are reading, students must also show a steadily growing ability to discern more from and make fuller use of text, including making an increasing number of connections among ideas and between texts, considering a wider range of textual evidence, and becoming more sensitive to inconsistencies, ambiguities, and poor reasoning in texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Writing: Text types, responding to reading, and research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standards acknowledge the fact that whereas some writing skills, such as the ability to plan, revise, edit, and publish, are applicable to many types of writing, other skills are more properly defined in terms of specific writing types: arguments, informative/explanatory texts, and narratives. Standard 9 stresses the importance of the writing-reading connection by requiring students to draw upon and write about evidence from literary and informational texts. Because of the centrality of writing to most forms of inquiry, research standards are prominently included in this strand, though skills important to research are infused throughout the document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Speaking and Listening: Flexible communication and collaboration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including but not limited to skills necessary for formal presentations, the Speaking and Listening standards require students to develop a range of broadly useful oral communication and interpersonal skills. Students must learn to work together, express and listen carefully to ideas, integrate information from oral, visual, quantitative, and media sources, evaluate what they hear, use media and visual displays strategically to help achieve communicative purposes, and adapt speech to context and task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Language: Conventions, effective use, and vocabulary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Language standards include the essential "rules" of standard written and spoken English, but they also approach language as a matter of craft and informed choice among alternatives. The vocabulary standards focus on understanding words and phrases, their relationships, and their nuances and on acquiring new vocabulary, particularly general academic and domain-specific words and phrases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Appendices A, B, and C&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appendix A contains supplementary material on reading, writing, speaking and listening, and language as well as a glossary of key terms. Appendix B consists of text exemplars illustrating the complexity, quality, and range of reading appropriate for various grade levels with accompanying sample performance tasks. Appendix C includes annotated samples demonstrating at least adequate performance in student writing at various grade levels.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <date>2014-02-15 19:10:01 UTC</date>
</page>
